Temperance mss., 1859-1885 LMC 2602
Lilly Library
Temperance mss.
1859-1885
Lilly Library
Central Association for Stopping the Sale of Intoxicating Liquor on Sundays
LMC 2602
1 Box 1 standard
The Temperance mss., 1859-1885, consists of over two hundred letters and signatures, as well as some images, relating to the Temperance Movement in Britain.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
The Temperance Movement was a social movement against the sale or drinking of alcoholic beverages. In Britain, the movement reached its peak in the mid-to-late 1800s, as alcohol consumption and alcohol-related violence was a wide-spread problem. Advocates formed numerous societies and associations to combat alcoholism, each group with their own ideas about how to go about stamping out the problem. Some advocated moderation in drinking, while others espoused complete abstinence; some focused on the religious message of temperance, while others sought to put pressure on the government to pass temperance legislation. The Central Association for Stopping the Sale of Intoxicating Liquor on Sundays, centered in Manchester, England, focused on petitioning Parliament to pass legislation that would close public houses and bars on Sundays. During the 1860s and 70s, the issue became highly politicized as the Temperance Movement became closely tied to the aims of the Liberal Party.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Correspondence; II. Signatures; III. Other.
Scope and Content Note
The Temperance mss., 1859-1885, consists of over two hundred letters and signatures, as well as some images, relating to the Temperance Movement in Britain. The letters date predominantly from the 1870s, a time when the Temperance Movement was emerging as an important political force in Great Britain, and are principally addressed to Edwin Barton and Robert Whitworth, leading figures in the Temperance Movement in north-west England and honorary secretaries for the Central Association for Stopping the Sale of Intoxicating Liquor on Sundays. The majority of the letters are written by politicians, relating to petitions to stop the sale of intoxicating liquors on Sundays.
Acquisition Information
Acquired 2008
Temperance --Great Britain --Societies, etc. --History --19th century.; Temperance --Great Britain --History --19th century.; Temperance and religion--Great Britain.; Prohibition--Great Britain--19th century.; Alcoholism--Great Britain--19th century.; Great Britain--History--Victoria, 1837-1901--Sources.; Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891--Photographs.; Hall, Samuel Romilly, 1812-1876.--Photographs.; Central Association for Stopping the Sale of Intoxicating Liquor on Sundays.; Barton, Edwin, fl. 19th century.; Whitworth, Robert., fl. 19th century.; Martin, Robert.; Balfour, Clara Lucas, 1808-1878.; Brassey, Thomas Brassey, Earl, 1836-1918.; Bright, John, 1811-1889.; Cecil, Eustace, Lord, 1834-1921.; Egerton, Wilbraham Egerton, Earl, 1832-1909.; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898.; Grossmith, George, 1847-1912.; Home, D. D. (Daniel Dunglas, 1833-1886.; Lubbock, John, Sir, 1834-1913.; Miall, Edward, 1809-1881.; Nugent, James.; Pease, Arthur A.; Rathbone, William, 1787-1868.; Spurgeon, C. H. (Charles Haddon), 1834-1892.; Stevenson, A. G.; Vivian, A. Pendarves (Arthur Pendarves), 1834-1926.; Woods, Henry, 1846-1921.; License Amendment League.
- Correspondence (Folder 1)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  General
  Transcriptions of the letters are available in each folder.
  - 1859-1869 (Folder 1)
    Correspondents include:
    - Bisley, Hugh, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Brown, H. P., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Cocker, Rev. Dr., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Cooke, Rev. Dr. William, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Cameron, Angus, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Delaran, Edward G., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Dorn, Neal, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Egerton, Wilbraham, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Gladstone, William Edwart, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Home, D. D., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - McKerrow, Rev., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - McKinton, John, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Nugent, James, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Smith, M. A., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Spurgeon, C. H., (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Strong, William Henry, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Thompson, George, (1 item) (Folder 1)
    - Whitworth, Robert, (1 item) (Folder 1)
  - 1870 (Folder 2)
    - Archbishop Thompson, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Bazley, Thomas, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Beales, Edmond, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Broadley, A.H.H., (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Farrar, John, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Hamilton, George, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Hick, John, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Johnstone, Harcourt, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Manners, John, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Miall, Edward, (1 item) (Folder 2)
    - Patten, Wilson B., (2 items) (Folder 2)
    - Rylands, D., (1 item) (Folder 2)
  - 1871 (Folder 3)
    - Balfour, Clara Lucas, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Caine, William, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Charley, W. Thaddeus, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Grey, Lord, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Hargraves, Joseph, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - James, John H., (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Manners, John, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Martin, Baron, (1 item) (Folder 3)
    - Willes, Justice, (1 item) (Folder 3)
  - March 1872 (Folder 4)
    - Broadley, A. H. H., (1 item) (Folder 4)
    - Crawford, Edward, (1 item) (Folder 4)
    - Walpole, J., (1 item) (Folder 4)
  - April-May 1872 (Folder 5)
    - Bar, R. B. Wingfield, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Brassey, Lord Thomas, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Brocklehurst, William, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - DuPre, Caledon G., (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Egerton, Algernon, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Egerton, Lord Wilbraham, (2 items) (Folder 5)
    - F. A. Stanley A. D. C., (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Fields, Joshua, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Hadfield, George, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Henry, John Snowdon, (2 items) (Folder 5)
    - Hornby, G. K., (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Mirry, James, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Powell, Francis Sharp, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Rathbone, William, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Stevenson, A.G., (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Tollemache, Wilbraham Frederick, (1 item) (Folder 5)
    - Woods, H., (2 items) (Folder 5)
  - Undated Letters., 1880-1885 (Folder 6)
    - Bright, John, (1 item) (Folder 6)
    - Dawson, George, (1 item) (Folder 6)
    - Cecil, Lord Eustace, (1 item) (Folder 6)
    - Grossmith, W., (1 item) (Folder 6)
    - Yorke, Charles Philip, 5th Earl of Hardwicke, (1 item) (Folder 6)
  - Letter Fragments (Folder 7)
    - Bagley, Thomas, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Clegg, Thomas, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Coke, William, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Cook, Thomas, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Daines, Edwin, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Hewlett, E., (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Home, D. D., (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Jackson, J., (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Jones, Joseph, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Moel, Leland, (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Morgan, J., (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Mosley, S., (1 item) (Folder 7)
    - Patten, Wilson, (1 item) (Folder 7)
- Signatures (Folder 8)
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Signatures (A-I) (Folder 8)
    - Ackroyd, Edward, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Ashworth, John, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Balfour, Clara Lucas, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Binley, Hugh, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Cecil, Lord Eustace, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Bright, John, (2 items) (Folder 8)
    - Brocklehurst, William, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Brown, Hugh Stowell, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Caine, William, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Charley, W. T., (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Close, Dean, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Corbett, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Crawford, Edward S., (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Dawson, George, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - DuPre, Caledon, G., (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Eardley, Robert, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Edwards, Dr., (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Egerton, Wilbraham, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Farson, Rev. John, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Fielden, Joshua, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Gladstone, William Edwart, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Lord Grey, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Hannah, John, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Hargraves, Joseph, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Marquis of Hartingon, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Henry, Fitz, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Holt, James Maden, (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Home, D.D., (1 item) (Folder 8)
    - Hornby, G. K., (1 item) (Folder 8)
  - Signatures (J-Q) (Folder 9)
    - Johnstone, Harcourt, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Lelegg, Thomas, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - The Bishop of Lincoln, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Lubbock, Sir John, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - The Bishop of Manchester, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Mandella, A.J., (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Manners, Lord John, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Manning, H. E., (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Martin, Baron, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - McKerrow, Dr., (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Merry, James, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Meyrich, Thomas C., (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Miall, Edward, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Mosley, Sam, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - The Bishop of Oxford, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - The Bishop of Peterborough, (1 item) (Folder 9)
    - Potter, Thomas B., (2 items) (Folder 9)
    - Powell, Francis S., (1 item) (Folder 9)
  - Signatures (R-Z) (Folder 10)
    - Rathbone, William, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Rylands, Peter, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Sandley, C., (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Selby, W. G., (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Shan, Richard, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Spurgeon, Rev. L. A., (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Stevenson, A. G., (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Thompson, George, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Tollemache, W. F., (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Vivian, Arthur Pendarves, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Walpole, J., (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - The Marquis of Westminster, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - Willes, Justice, (1 item) (Folder 10)
    - The Archbishop of York, (1 item) (Folder 10)
- Other (Folder 11)
  - Binding (Folder 11)
    - Front and back boards only. Purple-grey cloth, black leather at top and bottom corners (Folder 11)
  - Images and Miscellaneous (Folder 12)
    - Dean Close (Folder 12)
    - Rev. Dr. Crowther, Bishop of the Niger, England's First Black Bishop. (Folder 12)
      Bishop Crowther was the first African bishop in the Anglican Church.
    - Rev. Samuel Romilly Hall, President of the Wesleyan Conference. (Folder 12)